A Finding Aid to the Ching Ho Cheng papers, 1954-2014, bulk 1970-1989, in the Archives of American Art AAA.chenchin
Archives of American Art
Ching Ho Cheng papers
bulk 1970-1989
1954-2014
AAA.chenchin
Archives of American Art
2.9 Linear feet
The papers of New York City Asian American artist Ching Ho Cheng measure 2.9 linear feet and date from 1954 to 2014, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1970-1989. The collection documents his art career and life through biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, printed material, a scrapbook, photographs, artwork, and a sketchbook.
Cheng, Ching Ho
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1970s-1989 (0.1 linear foot; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1965-2014 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1986-2010 (0.1 linear foot; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1954-2011 (1.3 linear feet; Box 1, 2, 4, OV 5)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1982-1983 (0.1 linear foot; Box 2)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1970s-1980s (0.2 linear feet; Box 2, 4)
Series 7: Artwork and Sketchbook, circa 1960s-1980s (0.6 linear feet; Box 2, 3, OV 6)
Biographical/Historical note
Ching Ho Cheng (1946-1989) was a naturalized Asian American artist of Chinese descent who worked primarily in New York City.
Cheng was born in Cuba but spent most of life in New York City. After receiving his BFA from the Cooper Union in 1968, Cheng lived in Paris and Amsterdam, where he had his first solo exhibition in 1976. Shortly after, Cheng moved back to New York City. He became associated with the Warhol circle, and took up residence in the Chelsea Hotel, where he lived until his death from HIV in 1989. Cheng’s long-time companion was art historian Gert Schiff.
Working in the pop psychedelic style early in his career, Cheng later developed a technique of creating abstract paintings with stencils and torn paper that he treated and soaked. He was in more than fifteen exhibitions before his death, and his work has been collected posthumously by the Hirshhorn, the Whitney, and many other museums.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Ching Ho Cheng papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2014 by Sybao Cheng Wilson, Cheng's sister and executor of the Ching Ho Cheng estate.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York City Asian American artist Ching Ho Cheng measure 2.9 linear feet and date from 1954 to 2014, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1970-1989. The collection documents his art career and life through biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, printed material, a scrapbook, photographs, artwork, and a sketchbook.
Biographical materials include artist's statements, lists, his naturalization documents, and death certificate. Correspondence makes up a significant part of the collection and includes correspondence with family, friends, and artists, including Vali Myers, Tally Brown, Ira Cohen, David Rattray, and Dui Seid, Cheng’s close friend and classmate from the Cooper Union. Personal business records concern his estate and also include scattered receipts, contracts, and other agreements. Printed materials include exhibition catalogs and announcements, books, magazines, journals, newsletters, and clippings featuring Cheng and his work. One scrapbook contains clippings and reproductions of Cheng's work. Photographs are of artwork, portraits of Cheng, friends including Gregory Millard and Gert Schiff, and family. Artwork contains one sketchbook, a drawing, stencils, and a leather bag.
Brown, Tally; Cohen, Ira; Myers, Vali, 1930-2003; Rattray, David; Seid, Dui; Asian American artists; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks
- Biographical Material, circa 1970s-1989; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material dates from circa 1970s to 1989 and includes artist’s statements, biographical writings, lists, a passport, death certificates, and naturalization paperwork.
  - Artist's Statements and Biographical Writings, circa 1970s-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Supply Lists, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Contact Lists, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Life and Death Documents, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Naturalization, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1965-2014; Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence dates from 1965-2014 and includes letters and postcards from Cheng’s friends Vali Myers, Tally Brown, Ira Cohen, David Rattray, and Dui Seid; and from his sister and father. Mixed in with letters are exhibition flyers, photographs, and 2 limited edition publications by Ira Cohen, published by the Bardo Matrix Press in Kathmandu, Nepal. Also included are notes from Barbara, Cheng's psychic throughout the 1970s. Several folders contain letters from Cheng to friends, primarily Dui Seid. This series also includes professional correspondence from galleries and museums to Cheng or his estate, managed by his sister Sybao Cheng Wilson. One file contains condolences sent to Gert Schiff after Cheng’s death.
  - Letters to Cheng from Friends and Family, circa 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
  - Letter to Tim Engram from Cheng, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Dui Seid from Cheng, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Letters to Gert Schiff from Friends, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Professional Correspondence, circa 1970s-2014 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Personal Business Records, 1986-2010; Series 3; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Personal Business Records date from 1986-2010 and contain information about the Ching Ho Cheng estate, and other documents relating to his work including receipts, contracts, and loan agreements.
  - Estate and Will, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Personal Business Records, 1986-2010 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Printed Material, 1954-2011; Series 4; 1.3 Linear feet Box 1, 2, 4, OV 5
  Printed Material dates from 1954-2011 and is comprised of reference books and exhibition catalogs, announcements, books, magazines, journals, newsletters, clippings, press releases, and posters featuring Cheng and/or his friends.
  - Book, The Bloodleaf by David Rattray, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Books, 1976-1994 (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
  - Clippings, 1974-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, Tally Brown, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ephemera from Greechies, a play by Gregory Millard, circa 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1976-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1978-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Magazines, 1972-1992 (Box 2, Folder 7-12)
  - Newsletters, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper, The Soho News, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pamphlet, Cleveland Museum of Art, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Press Releases, 1976-1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Reference Books, 1954-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Oversize Book, Milk n' Honey by Mati Klarwein, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Clippings from Box 2, Folder 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Oversize Magazines from Box 2, Folders 7-10 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Oversize Posters, 1976-1985 (Box OV 5)
- Scrapbook, 1982-1983; Series 5; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  The scrapbook dates from 1982-1983 and contains clippings and reproductions of Cheng’s work.
  - Scrapbook, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Photographs, circa 1970s-1980s; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2, 4
  Photographs date from circa 1970s-1980s and include portraits of Cheng, friends including Gregory Millard, and his sister. The photograph album consists of Cheng’s work, travel pictures, and friends, including Gert Schiff. Also included are UFO photographs, references for his later works.
  - Ching Ho Cheng, Family, Friends, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Oversize Album, circa 1980s (Box 4)
  - Oversize Ching Ho Cheng from Box 2, Folder 20 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Photograph and Transparency, UFO, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Artwork and Sketchbook, circa 1960s-1980s; Series 7; 0.6 Linear feet Box 2, 3, OV 6
  Artwork dates from circa 1960s-1980s and includes one sketchbook, a drawing, stencils, and a leather bag like those he made and sold in the 1960s.
  - Drawing, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Leather Bag, 1960s (Box 3)
  - Stencils, circa 1980s (Box OV 6)